<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>films on Chen Li</title><link>https://chenlinear.github.io/tags/films/</link><description>Recent content in films on Chen Li</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chenlinear.github.io/tags/films/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>RARBG Shuts Down</title><link>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20230531-rarbg-shuts-down/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20230531-rarbg-shuts-down/</guid><description>RARBG shuts down, and here&amp;rsquo;s their announcement:
Hello guys,
We would like to inform you that we have decided to shut down our site.
The past 2 years have been very difficult for us - some of the people in our team died due to covid complications,
others still suffer the side effects of it - not being able to work at all.
Some are also fighting the war in Europe - ON BOTH SIDES.</description></item><item><title>Qingchun</title><link>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20230528-qingchun/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20230528-qingchun/</guid><description>I don&amp;rsquo;t really think awards are that important, but here goes my wildest guessing:
Qingchun (2023) is elected into Main Competition in the Cannes Festival this year. It has been 4 years since the last Chinese film, Nanfang chezhan de juhui (2019), was elected. Before that, there is only Chinese film that won the Palme d&amp;rsquo;Or, which is Ba wang bie ji (1993), directed by Kaige Chen, 30 years ago.</description></item><item><title>There Will Be Blood, A Brighter Summer Day, Evangelion</title><link>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20230304-there-will-be-blood-a-brighter-summer-day-evangelion/</link><pubDate>Sat, 04 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20230304-there-will-be-blood-a-brighter-summer-day-evangelion/</guid><description>Spoiler Alert!
This article is a comparison between There Will Be Blood, A Brighter Summer Day and Evangelion (Only TV and Old film this time). We should talk about why good things are good instead of why bad things are bad, because what really matters is the good, not the bad, or the ugly. And most of the time it&amp;rsquo;s not even bad or ugly, it&amp;rsquo;s just boring. This three films/anime are the best work I have watched and I want to know why I like them.</description></item></channel></rss>