<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    
    <title>Chen Li</title>
    <description>Chen Li&#39;s personal blog</description>
    <link>https://chenlinear.github.io</link>
    
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Copyright 2025, Calvin Tran</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Hugo - gohugo.io</generator>
    <docs>http://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs>
    <atom:link href="https://chenlinear.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/>
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Presuppositions of Physics Simulations</title>
      <link>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20240901-presupposition-of-physics-simulations/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t done a simulation project, but these are my presuppositions of simulation. Let&amp;rsquo;s see how they would change over time (haha pun intended).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-simulation-in-general&#34;&gt;§1 Simulation in General&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We divide space into several grids, but we also have Adaptive Mesh Refinement, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.05438&#34;&gt;[2312.05438] &lt;em&gt;Adaptive mesh refinement in binary black holes simulations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Also, there are &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adaptive_step_size&#34;&gt;Adaptive step size&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Butterfly Effect: &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13881&#34;&gt;[2401.13381]&lt;em&gt;Spontaneous stochasticity amplifies even thermal noise to the largest scales of turbulence in a few eddy turnover times&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 3 kinds of simulation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;radiative processes, spectrum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dark matter halos, n-body/test particle, gravity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;source population, luminosity distribution, redshift. neutrino in the universe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-language&#34;&gt;§2 Language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://benchmarksgame-team.pages.debian.net/benchmarksgame/performance/nbody.html&#34;&gt;n-body - Which programs are fastest? (Benchmarks Game)&lt;/a&gt;, like that&amp;rsquo;s even a question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-memory-usage&#34;&gt;§3 Memory Usage&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particle n-body simulation, because of the shape of the tensor &lt;code&gt;[num_particles, num_properties]&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;num_properties&lt;/code&gt; refers to $x$, $y$, $z$, $v_x$, $v_y$, $v_z$, spin, etc) does not change, the memory usage is almost const.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, if we encode time in this tensor, we should put it in the first dimension such that &lt;code&gt;[time_steps, num_particles, num_properties]&lt;/code&gt;. Because now if we want to take a picture from the video, we just do &lt;code&gt;x[time_step]&lt;/code&gt;. In terms of semetic, this feels natural. In terms of meaning, this shows that, time is just a set of tensors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- Can we use `torch.nn.Linear` to do the simulation? --&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-framework&#34;&gt;§4 Framework&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;41-run&#34;&gt;§4.1 Run&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only use &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Functional_programming&#34;&gt;functional programming&lt;/a&gt;, instead of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Object-oriented_programming&#34;&gt;object-oriented programming&lt;/a&gt;. Because the latter one is not necessary and the previous one, without state and so on, is faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def one_step():
    ...

def save():
    ...# save as `.parquet`?

for i in range():
    one_step()# the next step is determined by the previous step, so GPU is not much useful here
    save()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;42-plot&#34;&gt;§4.2 Plot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plot the animation of the simulation, and plot the variation of derived properties such kinetic energy, potential energy and so on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;def plot_animation():
    ....

def plot_kinetic_energy():
    ...

def plot_potential_energy():
    ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
      <author>Chen Li</author>
      <guid>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20240901-presupposition-of-physics-simulations/</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1.58</title>
      <link>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20240710-1-58/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-Xfv5NNPbLs&#34;&gt;Sabine mentioned today&lt;/a&gt; that the &amp;ldquo;dimension&amp;rdquo; of &lt;strong&gt;fractal&lt;/strong&gt; is $log{(\frac{3}{2})} \approx 1.58$, which reminds me about this LLM quantization method called &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17764&#34;&gt;BitNet&lt;/a&gt; with ternary {-1, 0, 1} parameter thus 1.58 bit. I would assume the only connection here is just the number.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      <author>Chen Li</author>
      <guid>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20240710-1-58/</guid>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physics Intuition</title>
      <link>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20240630-physics-intuition/</link>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had an argument with a friend the other day. He&amp;rsquo;s quitting physics and will be teaching high school, which in my opinion is more of less a waste of talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-complexity-or-why-most-physics-work-is-writing-code&#34;&gt;§1 Complexity, or Why Most Physics Work is Writing Code&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is our differences: He thinks most people in the physics business are doing something he does not like, which is writing code. For example, in his CP violation paper, what he mostly did is to get familiar with the code base. In his opinion, people should have physics intuition to come up with different theories and test it in experiments. Most of what we beginners do is the latter part, in other words, writing code. But my point is that physics has changed a lot and can not devolve back into the 20th century. The 21st century is about complexity:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Theories that are complicated, intertwined and conflicted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time: Experiments take decades now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Money: Newton did not need millions of dollars to buy lenses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With complexity comes with communication, which is inherently inefficient.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computers do so much more than line fitting, which is not achievable by human labor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared with this list, writing code does not seem so bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sorry nature does not allow analytical solution for crystal lattice so that we use approximations and computer simulations, but there is just no other way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of me blame the education system for a little bit: in undergrad, physics history in textbooks stops at mid-20th century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BTW, in &lt;em&gt;The Three Body Problem&lt;/em&gt;, if the Trisolarans write simulation program of their three body solar system, at least they can predict the movement of the solar system in the next decade or so. In the meantime, they can continue to observe the movement of the solar system and modify the &lt;code&gt;CONSTANT&lt;/code&gt; of the program for better precision, such as the mass of each sun and their distances between each other. Also, in order to get better precision, they can replace Newtonian dynamics with General Relativity. Thus given their highly-advanced technology (near-light-speed travel and so on), there&amp;rsquo;s no need to leave their solar system and come to our solar system. Yes there&amp;rsquo;s no analytical solution for the three body problem, but simulation is really useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I said decade or so in the last paragraph, I don&amp;rsquo;t know the specific time the program can predict, but I assume they evolved to intelligent beings thus must have a relatively long stable time. Maybe I can do a lot of simulations and take a mean value. And a more analytical method would be finding the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saddle_point&#34;&gt;saddle point&lt;/a&gt; in the system, as Poincaré did. Anyway, we only have one sun in the solar system so I&amp;rsquo;m not interested really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-i-have-trust-issues-with-my-physics-intuition&#34;&gt;§2 I Have Trust Issues (with My Physics Intuition)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout our argument, one term he kept using is &amp;ldquo;comprehension&amp;rdquo;. I kept saying I would prefer &amp;ldquo;hypothesis&amp;rdquo;. I think this tells the difference between us. You see, I don&amp;rsquo;t trust my intuition at all. Because at the end of day what we do is guessing, systematically guessing through math yes, but still guessing. I am being so cynical mostly because of my experience, and Immanuel Kant. (BTW, I heard undergraduate philosophy education stops at Descartes, the 17th century.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All physics intuitions are wrong, but some are more wrong. I read this article &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.math.columbia.edu/~woit/wordpress/?p=14013&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Physical Intuition vs. “Math”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; today, and the author wrote so many awesome examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- All models are wrong, but some are useful. -- George E. P. Box --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am so happy to announce: I have trust issues. And I don&amp;rsquo;t need intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-be-constructive&#34;&gt;§3 Be Constructive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just some notes for myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write code: You&amp;rsquo;re speaking three languages: the physics experiment language, programming language and physics theory language. Beware nobody else is trilingual, not even your professor, especially not your professor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read papers. Not about the math though, more about ideas and directions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show up to meetings and listen to people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put physics models in your brain cache the whole time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- Marshall: If I died under suspicious circumstances then beware. Trust no one, not even Ted. Especially not Ted. -- HIMYM S03E02 --&gt;</description>
      <author>Chen Li</author>
      <guid>https://chenlinear.github.io/posts/20240630-physics-intuition/</guid>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
